so this
is a suitor in the anguttara nikaya book
of sevens
7.49
that's in regard to seven perceptions
that are encouraged to be developed
the first one is the perception of a
suba or the non-beautiful
or the non-beautiful
i'll just call it the ugly
when the perception of the ugly is
developed and frequently practiced it is
of great fruit and great benefit
so when a biker often lives with such a
purpose his mind shrinks back and
his mind shrinks back and
goes in the opposite direction and turns
away from engaging in sexual intercourse
so either equanimity
or the opposite direction of what the
mind is attending to
gets established if he practices this
subaru so either his mind turns away
from sexual intercourse or
he he gets based in equanimity
or his mind gets established in that
opposite direction
of what of what he's attending to which
is beautiful
right so and that party term is
particular usually translated as repulsive so his
usually translated as repulsive so his
mind gets established in the repulsive
but it's it's the other side
the other side of what he's attending to
so it's the other side of what is being
attacked against
against the directly opposite
as in the opposite side of the beautiful
so the side that's simultaneously there
yeah not the opposite side in response
to beauty
so that's the point there the opposite
side how how would you know well in order to
how how would you know well in order to
define an opposite
you need to have that thing that this
opposes it
so the whole point of the opposite side
is to recognize that
the ugly is present
opposite to the beautiful while
beautiful is there
it's not something you need to find
like um in response to beautiful but
it's more like something you need to
discern within the beautiful as the
opposite side
like you know if you say the two sides
of the coin you don't seek the second
coin to see the other side of it it's the
to see the other side of it it's the
same coin
but now you need to see the opposite
side the one you're not looking at
and the reason why that's so important
is because most people most
commonly the way people practice the
asuba is in response
to the beautiful as in you want to get
rid of the beautiful and replace it with
the ugly
so those are just two separate things
for you you're not seeing that ugly
within that beautiful
which is how you would cancel the
beautiful by seeing the opposite of it
within it
but instead you're just trying to get
rid of the beautiful because it bothers
you and replace it with ugly because that's
and replace it with ugly because that's
supposedly not prodigy
or it shouldn't bother you as much if
you want to practice the
restraint but in in reality what you're
doing just acting on account of how
you're feeling
so the beautiful is there bothering you
and you just want to be free from bother
which is fine you want to be free from
bother but how you go about it do you go
about blaming the beautiful for the
bother well implicitly yes because you're
well implicitly yes because you're
trying to get rid of the beautiful by
replacing it with the ugly which you're
supposed to be
cultivating but that means you just
you you don't really know where the
bother is and the border is not in the
beautiful the lust is not in the beautiful none of
the lust is not in the beautiful none of
that is in the beautiful
it's in your own
lack of understanding of it not seeing
the nature of it attraction to it and so
on
because you because you don't see the
nature of that beautiful thing that's
what you're attracted to
exactly yeah yeah so and you will not
see the nature because now you think
oh the attraction the whole thing is in
the beautiful so all i need to do is
replace the beautiful with these images
of ugly
and then i'm free from attraction no and
that's exactly what happened to many
monks who were practicing wrongly then
they started getting attracted
to the ugly yeah to the disgusting
things to corpses and so on
because they were wrongly attending
again the art so the right attention the
rocket the attention of the opposite side or
the attention of the opposite side or
this side is not in the things
it's how you attend those things within
them so
while beautiful is present you have a
chance to discern
correctly that like jonaso kada
to attend correctly to attend to the so
the opposite side of it that is there
implicit which is why freedom from the
side that is beautiful
is possible
so you don't you don't have to do
anything in response to it
you just need to see through it and
that's why if you actually develop that
uh doesn't matter what type of beautiful
perception you encounter later on in the
future the mind remains equally developed in
the mind remains equally developed in
regard to it the mind sees through it
because it has seen through its nature
so that that beautiful is just
is is based on that which is not
beautiful well it's inseparable from
yeah that's the thing
like you you will not necessarily see it
as based upon it
because you you start with the beautiful
being put first
the nature of ignorance it shouldn't be
first but being put first is there's no
but being put first is there's no
there's no first point
there's no uh it's beginningless the
attitude that putting the beautiful
first assuming the beautiful you shouldn't be
assuming the beautiful you shouldn't be
there because
if you look through it you'll just see
the ugly but it is there
because you start as a as a person with
a mind that's not free from ignorance
that's why if you're rooted you cannot
go back to it
because actually if you see through the
nature of beautiful
as inseparable from ugly then you
realize it's not beautiful it's just
less ugly
not as ugly but equally ugly which means
equally start serving as a basis for dispassion
and that that brings me to i want to say
when you read that first the opening
like oh he cultivates perception how
like how do you cultivate the perception
of ugly or whatever when you know
anybody talks about cultivating
perceptions how do you cultivate perceptions
how do you cultivate perceptions
what is the practice of cultivating
perceptions
right attending to them
attending to certain deceptions okay so
you can either
attend to the beautiful or you can
what else by knowing them so you want to
say you want to establish your mind in
the perception of ugly now
perception of ugly now
how would you how would you do that
how would you discern the opposite side
well look at the the context
see the bigger picture of what or that
whatever i'm finding beautiful
right so you need a beautiful first so
you and that's that's when the when
we would say you should like
keep rechecking
so to speak your mind or is there
lost in it now as in is there presently
a durian enduring attraction to
beautiful right here right now then the answer is
right here right now then the answer is
no but then it's like oh
but could there be lust
in this mind as in in the future
in the moments to come is my mind
uh liable
to become attracted again to something
of central nature so that's
it's not just about or now i have to go
and look or
taste or touch or engage in any form
with central objects in order to see the
ugly through it no quite the opposite
by not engaging through central objects
in censor string you get to see the
liability towards the attraction which is present
towards the attraction which is present
attraction
like you're not you will not be liable
to be attracted to things in the future
if that liability is not presently
enduring as a form of attraction already
so that's when people sometimes judge
how you you need to look uh almost like
how you need to flirt with your classes
to see to learn about them no
quite the opposite you're actually
flirting with he's giving into the
weakness by giving into the weakness
you're not going to see your liability
because you're already acting out of it
so you want to not engage with sexuality
and then see that another reflection
that will say so
is my mind liable to future arising of
these things
can lust greed aversion delusion arise
in this mind they're not here now
but could they be here and he says yes
they can be here
oh why will they say oh because i
haven't abandoned things right here
right now
on account of which last arises
which is
craving for depending how
which which angle you want to take in it
yeah but the point is you want to
recognize that
the possibility of last aversion
delusion manifesting in your experience
is already last aversion delusion in
your experience just on a subtler level
you don't need to wait for the central
last aversion delusion to say okay now i
have it
you need to restrain from it and then
recognize the possibility of those
things arising in the future
i mean how would you know this
possibility of lusterizing in the future
unless that possibility of lust is
already present
right here right now which is how you
know it
so if you can discern that possibility
so that's that's already that's
basically the roots of lust
see the possibility of last as the
buddha said is because
is there because basis for lust is there
you haven't abandoned it
so circumstantially you're not
particularly specifically experiencing
any lust right here right now
but the whole basis the whole domain of
being liable to last is still there
you haven't abandoned it which is why if
you look at it
can these things arise in the future yes
means ah i'm presently still maintaining
their basis
so when the conditions are right lust
will arise on account of the basis that
i'm maintaining
so that's the whole point
and that's what you but you recognize so
so what would be the basis
for last arising
the future lust arising
valuing exactly wedding of pleasure
and then so there's no pleasure no
you're not engaging in an essential
pleasure yet
you're maintaining the view that that
pleasure is
valuable or not even that you
it's enough to maintain the view that
that pleasure is not dangerous
and that's enough to maintain the basis
for future lust to rise not seeing
danger and that's exactly if you see the extent
and that's exactly if you see the extent
of the danger as the buddha would say
you free yourself from sensuality oh
this is the extent of gratification
for as long as i haven't understood the
danger the extent of the danger in
regard to that gratification
i did not claim i am fully free from
central desires
but when i understood the danger then
you understood the escape then he
claimed that he's fully free from
central desires
so within the beautiful the opposite
side of the beautiful is the danger
defined by that beautiful by the way
it's not a separate thing you have to
take on as a separate contemplation
as a result of of witnessing the
beautiful noise
there is the beautiful perception of
beautiful perception of attraction
perception of lust
enduring in this mind
within that i need to discern that thing
as dangerous
so you can already see that cultivation
of perception is not done on the
particular level
of this perception that perception is on
the level of the domain of perception
because you are perceiving the fact that
you are liable
to future lust the future centrality
that is a perception in your mind that
liability is seen
it's perceived and it's not in regard to
anything particular
experienced by eyes nose mouth ears and
so on
so that's that's the cool cultivation of
perceptions that's why
he called like in other so this
perception of light
perception of boundlessness none of
these things are specific
oh can you see boundlessness with your
eyes no you're impossible
so these perceptions are mental in
regard to the
the sense domain in regard to the eyes
and so on in regards to sense organs
so that's another thing it's not about
looking at this not looking at that
it's about seeing the liability
to pleasure to lust to craving on the
level of your mind perceiving there and
seeing perceiving the danger in it
that's another perception you develop
the danger within this perception is
also perception
and if you cultivate it long enough next
time your eye
sees beautiful the danger is seen
through that beautiful with your eyes
because you develop it sufficiently with
your mind
the significance of it before it's even
it was before the particular beautiful
thing exactly before that has been developed
exactly before that has been developed
before but what i'm saying is
if you're free from sensuality even when
particular essential thing has arisen
and seen
it's the dangerous thing not the
beautiful of it which requires ignoring
the danger
so that's what i mean you through
development of that right perception of
danger the opposite side implicit in it seeing
the opposite side implicit in it seeing
it
uh learning how to basically uh maintain
in its enduring that will culminate to
the point of
where you will stop putting that
beautiful first
that will stop being the reference point
now it's the danger and the ugliness is
the reference
point so then the difference is only
like uh
how ugly and how dangerous it is not
like it's not dangerous
it's beautiful and sometimes gets no
it's always ugly it's always dangerous
just sometimes it's more dangerous
sometimes it's less dangerous
either way you don't go near it
sometimes i'm near the poison sometimes
poison is far away either way i'm not
engaging with it because it's poison
yes so it says that opposite side gets
established once you once you have developed that
once you once you have developed that
perception
those are the things that your mind will
turn away from
yeah prospects of sensuality
you'll be dispassionate equanimous
towards so the development of perception
then means development of the right
means development of the right
characteristics
that are implicit in it but you choose
to ignore them
the main chief of those characteristics
being the danger
yeah the peril so that risk that sign of
the danger gets
established your mind is composed within
that knowledge that now you
you have it can't
forget about it no no because everything
is dangerous yeah so you don't need to
keep thinking danger danger danger
you just need to keep seeing hearing
smelling taste and touching danger
becomes implicit
in the same sense a possibility of
pleasure is implicit for the mind not
free from sensuality
well mind free from sensuality has
replaced the possibility for pleasure
with possibility of pain and danger and
something you will shy away from
so it's effortless but you don't need to
maintain your freedom from centrality
and protect it because that's not
freedom then
freedom means you're free you're
literally freed because you replaced it
correctly you reverse the order
and you fixed it so to speak you healed
it up
so it's learning how to and that's again
the subtle thing i'm trying to point out
here is that um
inevitably you have to start with like a
fabricating the perception of danger
upon centrality
that's dangerous is dangerous dangerous
and usually in response to sensuality
others the mind has perceived sexuality craves
the mind has perceived sexuality craves
he wants it
he wants the pleasure it's so painful i
must get rid of it i must get rid of it
i must get rid of it
for as long as you have that attitude
you will not be able to see through
that which you're trying to get rid of
because you don't want to get rid of
the um the centrality as the cause for
your bother
you want to get rid of your attraction
towards sensuality that's kind of
indifferent to your body
as the buddha said for the target the
beautiful things remain in the world
he still perceives this is beautiful
this is ugly this is what he used to
excite me now it doesn't so you don't
lose perception of what's agreeable
what's disagreeable but you lose
attraction to it
because you've seen the danger through
in that attraction too beautiful
but for as long as you're trying to
replace and get rid of the beautiful
you're not seeing the opposite side of
it so literally
the coin given to you you're so scared
of its face because you might have a
desire for it
so you try to get rid of replace the
coin but how can you then see what's behind
but how can you then see what's behind
it what's the other side of the coin
you need to allow it to endure that's
why sense restraint is absolutely not
negotiable because sensory strain is that pre-req
because sensory strain is that pre-req
prerequisite that sort of precondition
of you developing sufficient strength
to be able to allow the beautiful thing
if it has a reason you don't seek it out
but if it has and it will arise because
you're not free from sensuality
when it arises you don't want to get rid
of it you want to see through it and for
that he needs to endure
with that like a sharp exciting sort of
edge but if you have developed your
behavior beforehand as the buddha would
say you will not act out of it which means
you will not act out of it which means
you get to see it
and you get to see then your
responsibility for your own attraction
it's not in things it's your it's in
your own unchecked craving towards it
so that's how you get to see the asuba
of suba
through subaru
and you will not see that on the level
of of the
eye nose smell ears sound
and so on
those will remain agreeable or
disagreeable but when those are
agreeable within that
you want to know the danger of it
because it is there
that's how you transcend both sense
organs and sense objects
not just the sense objects
being developed in regard to your own
body as in seeing it for what it is
seeing the danger for it not cultivating
lust and passion and desire towards it
you know the similar like like a
beautiful young woman or a young man in
their youth and somebody puts a dead
snake around their neck
would they be like disgusted just like
get rid of it that's how you should
cultivate attitude towards your body
attitude towards your body
so it's like oh within this body that's
healthy that's okay that i don't see any problem
that's okay that i don't see any problem
with it at the moment
you need to like oh i i'm
you can't get rid of it so what you need
to do within that
because you only have one body so you
can just replace it with a more suitable
body for contemplation
and you certainly don't want to wait
until you get sick old and and falling
apart so how do you then practice this
so how do you then practice this
repulsiveness
attitude of non-lasting danger within
that which is you can't see that it's
repulsive and you will never see it as
repulsive because it's you
well you cultivated on the level of that
liability that we spoke about
you know this factually currently
healthy relatively young strong and so on body
relatively young strong and so on body
within that i mustn't try to get rid of
that because i can't
so within that i need to see the danger
of that
beautiful agreeable healthy life and so
on
you don't deny that exactly you will
fall into the denial if you try to
ugly ugly and visualize and just
visualize this disgust discuss
yeah now that's a separate thing and
you're not seeing it
on the relevant basis of beautiful
you're not seeing it through the
beautiful you're just doing it in
response to it
which means you're denying the first
thing of beautiful
so the next by denying the first things
of beautiful that you perceive
you're denying the basis for beautiful
denying seeing it which means you're
maintaining the basis of beautiful for
the future so even
so your practice of asuba will be valid
for as long as your determination lasts
to look it up they look at ugly look at
how they look at ugly there's no wisdom
coming out of it
because wisdom remains even when you
stop making the effort
right so you stop making the effort last
back your mind exactly which means towards
your mind exactly which means towards
why the buddha said which means
that an account of which the future lust
will manifest hasn't been abandoned in
me
so you abandon it by seeing the danger
within the beautiful
not by trying to replace the beautiful
yeah because it is there exactly you ever you
because it is there exactly you ever you
you didn't create it exactly
the arising they had nothing to do with
you that's what i mean you will
inevitably have to act
out of the attitude of denying it by
blaming it for your own attraction and
trying to get rid of it
and replace it with perceptions of asuba
because that's more awesome
you need to be restrained by body by
speech by mind
but then you need to allow it to endure
and that's the unpleasant bit
having sensuality endure you know and
[Music] and not act out of it and that's the
and not act out of it and that's the
the sadi patana if it's done rightly he
knows the mind of sensuality
mind or affected with sensuality as mind
effectiveness and child not
he knows his mind of sensuality and then
he gets rid of that centrality no he
knows it
for what it is the mind is in central
domain it's not his doing
but he's doing is if he does what if he
welcomes that domain
if he entertains it if he delights in it
if he acts out of it
so i will not get rid of the domain of
centrality you can't
but i will get rid of my delight my
attitude towards it which is why
the domain of centrality keeps coming
back because i keep welcoming it in
and same like when the buddha said
actually no the mara said to his daughters who
no the mara said to his daughters who
tried to see like sort of
entice the mind of the buddha he said oh
you're wasting your time i spent seven
years of getting back to him and trying
to get him out and
he's nowhere to be seen
so you stop engaging with it mata still
might be jumping around you're trying to
to entertain is that until basically he
sees that you're irreversible
it's impossible for you to step back
into that domain and then these things
will even stop
from appearing to you literally like
flies landing
when there is still like bad smell or
open wounds
now you might have healed by the flies
still trying to find the place where
they can land
oh the simulator would use this like a
crow trying to find the
no sorry the simile the mara used was
like a crow trying to find an
edible bit that he can bite on and he
kept coming back to it kept searching
kept digging
and in the end and then he gives up
after six seven years the mara gave up
yes seven years yeah but none of those
seven years were bothered for the buddha
because the border is never in the mara or mars
the border is never in the mara or mars
things the border is in you
like inadvertently through your own
choice lacking awareness lacking the danger
lacking awareness lacking the danger
perception of danger
wandering straight into mata's domain on
and on and on and then keeping yourself
there that's the thing that's that's the
that's the thing that's that's the
border
this is just nuisance like heat wind
rain perceptions are beautiful
so learning how to allow beautiful to
endure without acting out of it
can then reveal the other side or then
rather if you learn how to allow
beautiful to endure when it has a reason
not act out of it
know the beautiful know the mind
effective with sensuality as mind
affected with sensuality
then thoughts of asuba will actually
start to apply correctly
as the counterpart of this very same
thing here
counterparty doesn't deny the beautiful
just reveals its other side
so continuing in regards to those
perceptions that need to be developed
when abiku becomes accustomed to the
perception of death
their mind draws back from attachment to
life
and either equanimity gets established
or that other side gets established
so either he becomes quite dispassionate
or
again and that's exactly the same what
we discussed in the previous
section like um
you know you can even you you can afford
to to practice a suba
at the expense of denying suba but see
you can't practice
mindfulness of death and expense of
denying life
because you can you have to be alive in
order to practice mindfulness of death
so the perception of of that death is
counterpart of this life here so you can
just get rid of it in order to see what
death is
which is how people practice asuba
usually get rid of the sensuality and
then just
just hammer in a super super yeah look
at something
look at something else so now you must
just to
practice the perception of death you
must you must not be alive yeah
exactly and then look at it stare at it
for long the other
means the other side is there
simultaneously present at the same time
within this like within within whatever
you're attending so
the death is simultaneously present as
the other side of life
that you are alive right here right now
even if you don't attend it necessarily
you're not attending the fact that
you're alive you're just taking it for
granted that doesn't matter in its nature death
that doesn't matter in its nature death
is implicit
and it wouldn't be implicit if there is
no life in the same sense asuba would
not be implicit if there is no subaru
so if you actually instead of following
the direction that
taking your life for granted offers
you start discerning whenever there is
life death is implicit
and start developing that subtle
implicit opposite perception of death within the
opposite perception of death within the
life
you will experience this enchantment of
his life
it will be impossible for you to remain
attracted to life
see so you have to be able to see that
life exactly exactly you have to be in the
exactly exactly you have to be in the
same sense you have to be able to see
subaru for what it is
you can't practice asuba until you've
actually understood what sugar is
but you will not understand what suba is
because you just keep trying to get rid
of it because it's too painful
so that is that's super sorry is that
attraction it's not beautiful but it's
that for you there is no attraction without
for you there is no attraction without
suba yeah yeah so you can
you can be you can even but you can even
be attracted to
genuine asuba because you're seeing it
as soon
because of your your attraction but if
you're free from attraction
suba will still remain
but you wouldn't be attracted to it
so you have to be able to see the
phenomenon of the life
yeah to discern the implicit
danger to see the other side of it the
dangerous the other side of the coin not a
the other side of the coin not a
different coin not the second coin
the same coin
and then yeah you get to see the dangers
because it is dangerous if it weren't
dangerous the guru wouldn't said you
should abandon
it if you're not seeing the danger
it's because you are not seeing the
danger not because it's not dangerous
but that's something you need to take on
faith in the beginning
the buddha says it is dangerous and you
have nothing to lose
if you stop practicing towards seeing
the danger you can only gain
so then whatever you see it life
correctly
and whatever's happening in life you're
not you won't be taken
well you're impassioned by it yeah
because the passion is passion is not
the product of life
passion is product of you thinking
or having a view that that life is yours
that that life is in your control
that that life is not subject to change
that that life will not end that that
life will last forever
all these are implicit basically notions
that you have towards life
enhance passion so passion is because of
your notions
misconcept misconceptions about life
that's why you have passion towards life
you remove the misconceivings of life no
base for passion
but again as i said you cannot remove
the misconceivings
of life by denying life
you cannot remove misconceivings about
beautiful by trying to constantly get rid of it
by trying to constantly get rid of it
and denying it because it bothers you
you remove misconceivings by allowing
beautiful to endure and then working on
your misconceivings of it
in regard to it that's we said it many
times so they said like
if the central thought manifests he he
the man
and that's what people misunderstand oh
he does he doesn't work he gets rid of
it
he's like oh but how does he go about
getting rid of it
does it say he denies it no he gets rid
of it by not welcoming it
by not delighting in it by not
entertaining it
ah that's how you get rid of it like
indirectly so to speak you don't get rid
of it but i will not think this i don't
think this i will not think this
which is why you're thinking it
and that's why the that kind of denial
always results in buildup of
frustrations because you're
contradicting yourself
i will not think sensual thoughts which
thoughts the essential thoughts that
you're thinking because you don't want
to think that
so yes you get rid of it but how
you get rid of the central thoughts or
you get rid of the intoxication with
life by not carelessly welcoming it
by not carelessly welcoming it
delighting in it
entertaining it ah so it arises on its
own i will not welcome it doesn't mean i'll
i will not welcome it doesn't mean i'll
go out and chase it away or try to kill
it okay no
i will just make sure i remain mindful
of not welcoming it with any gesture
or any implication or any hint i will
not give in to welcome in this
and you do that long enough the thing
will go away and that's how you got rid
of it
and against it you don't have to go and
seek out uh you know
death or possibility because it's
already there so
that's the whole point of this you seek
out means you still imply
with your view that the problem is in
those individual things that you're now
seeking out to prove to yourself that
you're not subjected to them
yeah you're always closing from those
things you ask yourself
am i subject to this yes i mean he's
already there so why
what is there to seek out when it's
already there can future
last manifest in me in the future
yeah i'm not sure means yes unless you
know that it can't
that's the basis for yes it can
and that's already there right there
experience right there and then here
and now so what is there to seek so if
you seek out the individual
examples of lust or so on to prove
themselves that you're not lustful
means you're fully lostful and you still
think the problem is in those individual
things that you perceive
not in your mind of welcoming the
lighting entertaining it so you can ask
yourself am i
subject to death will i be affected if
my life were to end next second
yes there you go i don't know there you
go you will
so how can you then free yourself from
death without denying life
by seeing the danger in life and
removing slightest passion towards life
while the life is still there and then
you know ah
it's the passion that kept me bound to
life that's subject to death
not life in itself hence freedom from
life is possible
without needing to die and that's why
when you do die as i
would say you will not be reappearing
anywhere else
because you have severed any bond with
the entire domain
yes
death is where life is of any kind
if you remove slightest passion towards
that life there is no
basis for death to apply to you
another perception the perception
of the other side of eating
when you develop that perception
your mind draws back from the craving
for tastes
and or you just get economists
that's the same thing
developing the other side of eating or
the other side
of food consuming food
what else is there while you're eating
experiencing all these tastes and so on
what are all the reasons that you're
eating in the first place
you're the digest going down chewing
digesting yeah again all of that is
yeah again all of that is
is sort of um is secondary
to the point that you prioritize the
pleasure of eating
that's what you put first see when
you're starving
really really hungry
losing the sight of that as the reason
for your eating
you will be automatically eating out of
pleasure for the taste not of the need
for the food
so the other side of the eating is
doesn't matter how much you enjoy it
or not enjoy it is is something you have
to do
so it's a need
it's a necessity but
forgetting that it's a necessity or
rather taking for granted that necessity
taking for granted that necessity
covering it up as a necessity
you then get picky you then start
speaking tastes and start acting out of
taste but doesn't matter how much acting out
but doesn't matter how much acting out
of taste you go for
is still within the necessity you still
need to eat
yeah that's the horrible thing that's
the horrible thing exactly
i need to eat like the fact that hunger
is affecting you
body physically and if i don't i'm
destroying you
yeah so the pressure of eating is there
but you ignore that because you took
food for granted and then
on account of it you developed now uh
priority of tastes
yeah priority pleasure which is fully
within that need
so all you need to do is uncover the
need that you covered up as the first
and then taste is the second not the
other way around
but by covering up that need the
pressure the hunger
the unpleasantness of it that being
subjected to it
covering that up you put joy for the
taste first you put pleasure first it's like
first you put pleasure first it's like
it's like a slave
taking delight in the master somehow
well no
i'm guessing he's a slave yes forgetting
he's a slave and then taking delight in
the fact that he's
been beaten every day he has to do all
this work
yeah well more like more like uh finding
a preference
in how he's going to be beat in that day
forgetting that he has no choice about
being beaten
being subjected to discomfort
so it's like you're subjected to this
comfort if you go through beating beating stops
if you go through beating beating stops
for a bit then it comes back
but instead of seeing is there a way out
of this entire situation of being
subjected to beating in the first place
he just focuses on what would be the
agreeable ways of receiving my beating
that's that craving for taste yeah
exactly so instead of
investing his effort in finding the way
out of his slavery
all together he won't be receiving any
beatings any punishment
his efforts are invested in pursuing you
know maybe a silky whip
or something else that's not as as
as coarse as other forms of beat but
it's still something you have to go
through he's like oh
so through your own chasing of refined
forms of punishment
you keep yourself still bound to the
punishment
so that so food developing that
so that's only if you don't ignore the
fact that food
is a necessity that you are subjected to
it unpleasantly
you will then not lose the context of
why you eat
when you need to eat no matter how
agreeable or disagreeable the punishment
is
how much enjoyable this is it's still
within the unpleasant
not enjoying fact of hunger so when the
hunger disappears you stop eating
that's it yeah you see the disease of
that great what
the greatest disease is hunger wasn't it
it is affliction you keep constantly
afflicted by the hunger
yeah it's the greatest addiction yeah so
you just
your way of dealing with affliction is
not freeing yourself from being liable
to affliction altogether
you're always uh just finding the
pleasurable aspects of affliction
still affliction
you're not really dealing with anything
just covering it up
so that enjoyment of taste and cooking
and recipes that comes out of putting
that first
putting that that when you see that
other side that necessitate your food
passion will disappear yeah it seems
like quite a bit it would be like like
well it would be impossible to make the
effort towards it
towards the taste doesn't matter like
you will not taste it if something is
agreeable it's just it would be
impossible for any amount of agreeable
or disagreeable taste
to disturb your mind or to like tip
back that picture into putting first
which is second
and putting second which is first taste
is always second pleasure
the taste of displeasure of the test is
always second to hunger
to hunger but for you taste is the first
craving is the first
everything else is saying you don't
forget about honey you forget the cheese
out of hunger
which is why the people eating when
they're not hungry just seeking out a
taste because the taste is now the
criteria the pleasure of the taste is a criteria
the pleasure of the taste is a criteria
but doesn't matter how great how refined
the criteria you might have developed
is still within the need of hunger if
there's no need for
for food you wouldn't be engaging with food